# MD SOMIR KHAN

+1(409) 444-7531 | Lafayette, LA, United States | somirkhanshowrov@gmail.com | LinkedIn | Github

#### **OVERVIEW**

A graduate student pursuing an MS in Computer Science at the University of Louisiana at Lafayette with academic research experience in **Data Analysis**, **Machine Learning**, **and Natural Language Processing** and 3 years of experience in the software industry as a **Full Stack Engineer**. Key qualities include the ability to work independently, curiosity to learn new things and great oral and written communication skills.

#### **EDUCATION**

University of Louisiana at Lafayette Master of Science in Computer Science

Lafayette, LA, United States Jan 2023 - Present GPA: **3.90/4.00** 

- Thesis: Bibliometric Data Analysis and Mitigation of Authorship Abuse in Science (On-going)
- **Key Courses:** Design & Analysis of Algorithms, Neural Networks, Image Processing, IT and Network Security, Principles of Computer Communication and Networks

Khulna University of Engineering & Technology
Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Engineering

Khulna, Bangladesh March 2016 – March 2020 GPA: **3.22/4.00** 

- Undergrad Thesis: Sentiment Analysis for Bengali Sentences using CNN-BiLSTM model
- Key Courses: Algorithm Analysis and Design, Data Structures and Algorithms, Object Oriented Programming, Operating Systems, Database Systems, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Discrete Mathematics, Mathematical Analysis, Numerical Methods, Software Engineering and Information System, Computer and Network Security

#### RESEARCH PROJECTS

**Bibliometric Data Analysis and Mitigation of Authorship Abuse in Science** *Python, R, Pandas, Matplotlib, Selenium* MS Thesis (Current)

- Created a bibliometric dataset by collecting data from Google Scholar.
- Analyzing authorship trend and investigating ways for mitigating Authorship abuse.

**Application of Machine Learning on Selection of CPU scheduling dynamically** Python, Scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy MS Course Project

• Compared application of different machine learning classifiers like LDA, Decision Tree, Random Forrest to dynamically choose appropriate CPU scheduling technique to reduce operation time.

**Diagnosing Parkinson's Disease Using 1D CNN with DWT Coefficients**MS Course Project

Python, Keras, Pandas, Numpy, MATLAB

- Conducted an investigation into the potential use of Discrete Wavelet Transform (DWT) and Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) for the diagnosis of Parkinson's Disease (PD) based on gait data.
- Utilized publicly available gait data sets to test the proposed method and evaluated its performance.

**Sentiment Analysis on Bengali Sentences using CNN-BiLSTM Model** *Python, NLP, NumPy, Pandas, TensorFlow, Git*Undergrad Thesis

- Created a dataset of bengali sentences by collecting data from Youtube and former Twitter platform.
- Designed a model with Convolutional Neural Network with Bidrectional LSTM for analyzing positive and negative sentiment.

### OTHER PROJECTS

### Hand Gesture Controlled Wheel Chair

Raspberry Pi, Python, Arduino Uno

**Undergrad Course Project** 

• Developed a prototype vehicle with hand gesture control using a Raspberry Pi, Arduino Uno, and an Accelerometer to assist individuals with mobility challenges.

# STANDARDIZED TEST SCORES

GRE Nov 08 2021

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## **Graduate Teaching Assistant at the School of Computing & Informatics**

Lafayette, LA, United States

Jan 2023 - Present

University of Louisiana at Lafayette

- Course: Introduction to Data Structures & Software Design
  - \* Assisted course instructor in preparing exam questions and assignments.
  - \* Mentored students by one-on-one in person and virtual meetings.
  - \* Graded assignments of around 30 student every semester.

# **Software Engineer**

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Nagorik Technologies Ltd

Nov 2021 – Dec 2022

- Developed and deployed central payment gateway system for 12 Company products, reducing payment gateway integration time from 16 hours to 1 hour.
- Developed and deployed the backend and admin portal for 10 quiz-based applications, each with over 500,000 users.
- Worked on optimizing complex queries and caching on 6 applications.
- Coordinated communications and technical documentation between the development team and Marketing team.

## **Software Engineer**

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Mazegeek Technologies Ltd

Aug 2020 – Oct 2021

- Developed and deployed SaaS platform to integrate chatbots for order management and customer support on Face-book and Viber.
- Developed and deployed web application for SMS campaigns on mobile operator networks and Viber.
- Contributed to the development of an E-kyc web application focused on the extraction of information from National ID cards and the verification of individuals by matching their faces with the images on the National ID cards.
- Worked on data visualization for dashboards and reports.

### OTHER EXPERIENCE

## **Information Desk Staff at Student Union**

Lafayette, LA, United States

University of Louisiana at Lafayette

Jun 2023 - Jul 2023

- · Assisted students and visitors with inquiries and provided information about university services.
- Developed strong communication and interpersonal skills through interactions with diverse individuals.

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

**Languages:** Python, C++, C, Java, SQL, HTML, CSS, JavaScript.

**Frameworks:** TensorFlow, Keras, Scikit-learn, OpenCV, Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, seaborn, PyTorch, Git, Laravel, Vue.js, Nginx, AWS EC2, AWS S3.

#### AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Intra KUET Programming Contest 2019 7th position
- Intra KUET Programming Contest 2017 2nd position
- Higher Secondary Certificate General Scholarship 2015

#### VOLUNTEERING AND CO-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- Serving as a member of the Bangladeshi Student Association at ULL by organizing Bengali community festivals and helping new Bangladeshi students.
- Served as Vice President and General Secretary of the Cyber Gaming Club for a total of 2 years, where I organized gaming events, managed sponsors, and led event organization from 2016 to 2020 at the Khulna University of Engineering & Technology.
- Served as a member of the Organizing Committee for a Computer Science Festival organized by the Department of Computer Science at Khulna University of Engineering & Technology in 2019.
- Served as a Dream (Voluntary Blood Donation Society of KUET) member, where I donated blood and volunteered to manage blood donation and organize events from 2016 to 2020 at the Khulna University of Engineering & Technology.

# REFERENCES

#### Dr. Mehmet Tozal

Associate Professor School of Computing & Informatics University of Louisiana at Lafayette Lafayette, LA, United States E-mail: metozal@louisiana.edu

# H. M. Abdul Fattah

**Assistant Professor** 

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Khulna University of Engineering & Technology Khulna, Bangladesh

E-mail: hussainfattah@cse.kuet.ac.bd